<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tvvelve rules, and vveapons concerning the spirituall battel Together with a briefe exposition vpon the sixteene Psalme: with two most worthie epistles, written in Latin by that most worthy and noble gentleman Iohn Picus Earle of Mirandula. And translated into English for the benefite of all good Christian souldiers in the spirituall battaile.</title>
            <title>Selections</title>
            <author>Pico della Mirandola, Giovanni, 1463-1494.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19898A.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110418</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845967</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176514</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09628)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176514)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 339:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tvvelve rules, and vveapons concerning the spirituall battel Together with a briefe exposition vpon the sixteene Psalme: with two most worthie epistles, written in Latin by that most worthy and noble gentleman Iohn Picus Earle of Mirandula. And translated into English for the benefite of all good Christian souldiers in the spirituall battaile.</title>
                  <title>Selections</title>
                  <author>Pico della Mirandola, Giovanni, 1463-1494.</author>
                  <author>W. H., fl. 1589.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Windet, for Iohn Daldern, and are to be sold in Canon lane at the signe of the vvhite horse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: W.H.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19898+ on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176514:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176514:1"/>
            <p>TWELVE RVLES, AND VVEAPONS CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNING THE SPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RITVALL BATTEL.</p>
            <p>Together with a briefe expoſition vpon the ſixteene Pſalme: With two moſt worthie Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, written in Latin by that moſt worthy and noble Gentleman Iohn Picus Earle of Mirandula.</p>
            <p>And tranſlated into Engliſh for the benefite of all good Chriſtian Souldiers in the Spirituall battaile.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Windet for Iohn Daldern, and are to be ſold in Canon lane at the ſigne of the vvhite horſe. 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176514:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176514:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL, MY VERY GOOD VNCLE, SIR NICHOLAS BAGNOLL KNIGHT, KNIGHT MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of Ireland, one of her Maieſties coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Eſtate in that Realme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat our life is a fight and battell vpon the earth, (my very good vncle) both the holy Scriptures, &amp; our daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doe teach vs, but how litle wee regarde the warre whereunto we are waged, the ſacred &amp; honorable vow and profeſsion of Souldiers that we haue taken, the noblenes &amp; excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of the Generall that commaundeth vs, the iuſtnes and importance of the quarrell entred into by vs, the inexplicable reward and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph
<pb facs="tcp:176514:3"/>
(if we conquere) propoſed vnto vs, the might, malice, and pollicie of the forces bent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, the endleſſe diſhonor and ruine that we run into if they doe vanquiſh vs, the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhes that to that ende they lay for vs, the ſtratagems that they vſe towards vs, the hote and violent charges that they geue vs, the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of miſchiefes that they diſcharge at vs, the defection that they practiſe in vs, the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery that they pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt vs, the breach that they make in the innermoſt houlde of vs, and the fierce nd furious aſsaults wherewith they aſſaile vs, their ample and often conqueſtes, &amp; our moſt miſerable captiuities do too too much teſtifie. From the which, though dayly raunſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the bountie of our Generall, to allure vs to more value and vigilancie: wee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull, and vngratious, to our perpetuall ſhame (if we amend not) become more daſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and ſecure. Whereof foure cauſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from one Fountaine (the wante of Gods grace) may me thinkes be aptly produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>The firſt, ignorance of the warre, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that doe encounter vs. The ſecond, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of fortitude &amp; reſolution in the function
<pb facs="tcp:176514:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vndertaken by vs. Thirdly, the lack of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and weapon, and other neceſsaries that ſhould furniſh vs. Fourthly, the want of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall skill and diſcipline, that in any part and action of our ſeruice ſhould direct vs.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, we ought to conſider that there are three mightie campes enuironing of vs: the fleſh, the world, and the infernall forces, for we fight not onely againſt fleſh and bloud, but alſo againſt principalities, againſt powers againſt the worldly gouerners, the princes of the darkenes of this world, and against ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall wickedneſſes which are in the high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Theſe, vnder Sathan their ſoueraigne, whoſe kingdome is calamitie, whoſe ſcepter is ſinne, whoſe lawes are lies, whoſe triumphe is torments, whoſe wages to his ſouldiers is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall woe, and curteſie to his captiues is endleſse death and deſtruction: doe warre with vs in foure ſeuerall places. Firſt generally, against our head and hole armie: then particularly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the legion and Phalange wherein wee are inrolled: next peculiarly, againſt the ſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we are appointed vnto: lastly, they rayſe ciuill warres in our ſelues. Our Sauiour and ſoueraigne Chriſt Jeſus (whoſe kingdome
<pb facs="tcp:176514:4"/>
is euerlaſting bliſſe, whoſe ſcepter is righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whoſe law is trueth, whoſe triumphe is glorie, whoſe wages is celeſtiall ioy, and whoſe mercie to his elect is eternall life and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) hath himſelfe in perſon encountred with theſe our enemies, and breaking their force &amp; ſtrength to the r confuſion and ouerthrowe, hath after his moſt royall and bleſsed victory, aſcended into the Capitoll, and triumphant part of his kingdome, the heauenly and celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Hieruſalem: leauing vs ſuch directions, as if we follow, we ſhall alſo become through him, victorious, and ſo accompanie him euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly in his triumph. Jn the meane time (as it is laide downe by the Cronicler of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, S. <hi>Iohn Reuel. Cap. 12.</hi>) The dragon in his rage and furie, preuayling neither against the head, nor against the whole bodie of this armie, the better part whereof (now in triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph with their Generall) is out of gunſhot, purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his malice againſt the remnant of the host which keepe the commaundements of God, and haue the testimonie of Ieſus Chriſt. Theſe he aſſayleth firſt in a generalitie, euen the whole Militant Church, for whoſe good estate wee ought to labour and ſtriue in praiers and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications
<pb facs="tcp:176514:4"/>
vnto God, &amp; both defend and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the boundes thereof to our vttermoſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. Next, with force and fraude, by himſelfe, and his inſtruments, his vicar generall, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and his deluded kings and potentates: he attempteth the ouerthrow of euery principall part and phalange of her moſt excellent maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and her dominions, her highnes being in the ſame the Lords lieutenant, in whoſe moſt bleſsed gouernment and legions moſt conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous we are enrolled: wherein we ought with all care, fortitude, and induſtry, to reſiſt both his practiſes ſecrete, and his open hoſtilitie. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the ſtation appointed vs, and functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that we are called vnto, he ſtirreth troubles to afflict vs, enuy and malice to ſpight vs, detraction and ſlaunders to annoy vs, perils to enuiron vs, the fleſh to puffe, and yet to pine vs, the world to allure, and yet to abhorre vs: troubles we muſt ouercome with patience, enuy and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice with vertue, perils with magnanimitie, the fleſh with the ſpirite, the thornes and nettles of this world with the lillies and roſes of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; the hatred of men with the loue of God. Laſtly, he worketh a rebellion in our ſelues, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp the vices and corruptions of the first
<pb facs="tcp:176514:5"/>
               <hi>Adam,</hi> of whom we are borne in the fleſh, whoſe workes are adulterie, fornication, vncleannes, wantonnes, couetouſnes, idolatrie, witchcraft, hatred, debate, emulations, wrath, contentions, ſeditions, hereſies, enuy, murders, drunkennes, gluttony, and ſuch like: againſt the vertues and perfections of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> of whom wee are regenerated in the ſpirite: whoſe fruite is loue, ioy, peace, long ſuffering, gentlenes, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, faith, meekenes, and temperancie. He beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs from without with an army of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, vnder the banner of worldly vanitie: and aſsaultetb vs within with our owne ſclanes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the enſigne of fleſhly frailty. Againſt theſe villaines let vs redouble our vigor with indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and ſlaying them with the ſword of the ſpirite, let vs ſally out and diſcomfite vnder the ſtandard of our Soueraigne, both the worlde and the deuill, and all their complices: let vs herein ſhew our ſelues reſolute, vertuous, and valyant, and ſay with the Spaniard, <hi>No vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tud ſino vencar, no verdadera gloria ſino victoria.</hi> There is no vertue but in vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, there is no true glory but in victorie. Let vs labor to be endued with perfect fortitude, let vs conſider that it beſeemes not a noble
<pb facs="tcp:176514:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and generous minde to ground his value ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon hope of gaine, for that is marchant-like and mercenarie: or vpon feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for that is abiect and compulſarie: or vpon perſwaſion of aduantage for that is fox like and ſubtill: or vpon rankor and rage, for that is diueliſh and paſſionate: or vpon foole hardines and temeritie, for that is inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and ſenceleſſe: but vpon diſcharge of due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, loue of vertue, iuſtice of the quarrel, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the generall, and honor of the conquest. Let vs propoſe euen before our eyes the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite skill, the ſingular vertue, the ineffable authoritie, and the felicitie inexplicable of our king and ſoueraigne Chriſt Ieſus. Let vs ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to learne the firſt, to imitate the ſecond, to depend vpon the third, ſo ſhall we participate of the fourth. Let vs take vnto vs the whole armour of God, let our loynes be girded about with verity, let vs put on the breſt plate of righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes, let our feete be ſhod with the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the goſpel of peace: aboue all let vs take the ſhielde of faith (which is Chriſt Ieſus by faith apprehended) wherewith wee may quench all the fierie dartes of the wicked. Let vs take the helmet of ſaluation, and the ſworde of the
<pb facs="tcp:176514:6"/>
ſpirite, which is the word of God. Let vs pray alwayes with all maner prayers and ſupplication in the ſpirite, and watch thereunto with all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scipio Affricanus,</hi> as we reade in <hi>Liuie,</hi> for the better trayning of his Souldiers, preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed them the first day to runne certayne myles armed, the ſecond before their Tent doores to trimme and dreſſe their furniture, the third day to exerciſe them ſelues in a fayned velitation and skirmiſh one with the other, the fourth day to reſt, the fift day to returne to the firſt dayes prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: and thus to continue while they had leyſure from true battels and conflicts.</p>
            <p>But ſith this ſpirituall warfare is continuall, we may neuer lay off our armour, but must (like expert Souldyars) make it as familiar vnto vs as our skinne, eſpecially ſith it is of that neceſſity, that we cannot conquere without it, and of that mettal that it wil ruſt with no wether, &amp; of that nature that it wil wax the brighter the more that we weare it: We ſhall neede no counterfet skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, that are euer preſent with ſerious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats, wherein to winne is not weariſome, but to loſe is laborious: the one carrying with it ſolace, the other ſorrowe. Let vs learne carefully, and
<pb facs="tcp:176514:6"/>
obſerue faithfully, the directions geuen vs by our Generall, for his doctrine is our diſcipline. Let vs carry alwaies in minde his cohortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the whetſtone of martiall vigor. Let vs imitate his example, who is the perfect patterne of all goodneſse and vertue. Let vs be allured by the exploites of famous Souldiers that haue beene before vs. Let vs follow their courſe, their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, in this ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fight, wherein among many I greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the inſtructions and practiſe of that moſt rare, learned, vertuous and noble Gentleman, <hi>Iohn Picus,</hi> Earle of Mirandula, whoſe aduice herein ſo well pleaſeth me, that I thought good to communicate it to my friends, and to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it vnto you (my very good vncle) toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a briefe expoſition of his vpon the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Pſalme, with two Epistles vnto his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewe, a most honourable, vertuous and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Prince <hi>Iohannes Franciſcus Picus,</hi> Earl of Mirandula, and Prince of Concordia: which I preſent vnto you as the fruytes of mine idle houres, which being not many, their labour can be neither great nor exquiſite. It reſteth that I recommend you to his moſt bleſſed tuition that
<pb facs="tcp:176514:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hath hetherto led you a long and honourable race thorow the warfare, both ſecular and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall: ioyning with you in most feruent prayers to his diuine Maiestie, to eſtabliſhe your trauayles in the one throughout all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: and your triumphs in the other, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout all eternitie.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From the caſtle of the Iland, <date>this tenth of December. <hi>1588.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your louing Nephew W. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="rules">
            <pb facs="tcp:176514:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TWELVE RVLES OF IOHN PI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Earle of Mirandula, partly ſtirring vp, partly directing man in the ſpirituall battaile.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F THE WAY OF vertue ſeeme hard vnto man becauſe wee muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually fight againſt the fleſh, the deuill, and the world, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that what way ſoeuer hee ſhall chooſe, (yea if it be according to the world) hee muſt ſuffer much aduerſitie, ſorrow, diſcommoditie and trauaile.</p>
            <p>Let him remember that in thinges of this world, the fight is longer, painfuller, &amp; vnprofitabler, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in labor is the ende of labor, and the laſt is eternall paine.</p>
            <p>Let him remember that it is a fooliſh thing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that any is able to goe to heauen, vnleſſe it be through this ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ell, euen as our head Chriſt aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not into heauen but by his croſſe, neither ought the ſtate of the ſeruant to be better then the ſtate of his Lord and maſter.</p>
            <p>Let him remember that this battell is not onely to be endured, but alſo to be deſired, although there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we receiue no reward, onely to be conformed to Chriſt our God and Lord, &amp; as often as thou ſtriueſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176514:8"/>
againſt any of thy ſences by reſiſting any temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, marke to what part of the croſſe of Chriſt thou art to be conformed: as when thou, reſiſting gluttonie, annoyeſt thy taſte, remember that he dranke vinager mingled with gall: when as thou keepeſt thy handes from any rapine which liketh thee, remember that his hands were faſt nayled to the croſſe for thee: and if thou reſiſteſt pride, remember that when he was in the forme of God, hee tooke vpon him for thee the forme of a ſeruant, and humbled himſelfe euen to the death of the croſſe: and when thou art tempted of anger, remember that he which was God, and the moſt righteous among men, when he notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſaw himſelfe as a theefe, to be mocked, to be ſpitted on, to be beaten, to be reuiled, and to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted with theeues, yet he ſhewed at no time any to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of anger or grudge, but enduring all things moſt patiently, replyed to all men moſt mildly: and in this wiſe running thorow euery thing, thou ſhalt finde that there is no paſsion but ſhall make thee confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to Chriſt in ſome ſort.</p>
            <p>That thou truſt not in theſe twelue weapons in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worldly remedie whatſoeuer, but onely in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Ieſus Chriſt, which hath ſaid, Be of good chere I haue ouercome the world. And in another place, The Prince of this world is caſt out: wherefore we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by his onely power doe truſt that we are able both to vanquiſh the world, and to ouercome the deuill, therefore wee ought alwayes by prayer to ſeeke his helpe.</p>
            <p>Remember that when thou haſt ouercome one temptation, then another is alwayes to be expected, for that the deuill alwayes goeth about ſeeking who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deuoure: wherefore it behooueth vs alwayes to be readie and regardfull, and to ſay with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176514:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I will alwayes ſtand vpon my watch.</p>
            <p>That thou not onely be not ouercome of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, but that thou alſo ouercome him when he temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thee: and this is, when thou doeſt not onely not offend, but alſo takeſt an occaſion to doe ſome good by that thing wherin he tempteth thee: as if his work offereth thee any good, that thereby thou fall into vaineglorie, thou foorthwith conſidering it, not as thy worke, but as a benefite of God, doeſt humble thy ſelfe, and iudge thy ſelfe to be too little thankful vnto God for his benefites.</p>
            <p>That when thou doeſt fight, thou mayſt fight as though thou wert conquering, and thereby to haue euerlaſting quietnes, for that happily God of his grace wil geue this vnto thee, and the deuill ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne no more diſmayd by reaſon of thy victorie: and when thou haſt ouercome, liue as though thou were preſently to fight, that in battell thou bee alwaies mindfull of victorie, and in victorie alwaies mindfull of battaile.</p>
            <p>That although thou finde thy ſelfe in euery point well ſtrengthned and prouided, yet notwithſtanding thou ſhun alwaies the occaſions of offence, becauſe, the wiſe man ſaith, he that loueth danger, ſhal peariſh therein.</p>
            <p>That in temptations thou be alwaies ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the beginnings, and to daſh the babes of Babylon againſt the rock. The rock is Chriſt: for too late is the medicine prouided, if the euill be too farre gone.</p>
            <p>Remember that albeit in the very conflict of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, the fight ſeeme ſharpe and difficult, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it is farre ſweeter to ouercome, than to run into ſinne. Wherefore diſpoſe thy ſelfe to the victory. And in this many are deceiued, becauſe they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare not the ſweetenes of the victorie to the ſweetnes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176514:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of ſinne, but they compare the ſharpnes of the battel to the ſweetnes of pleaſure: and yet notwithſtanding m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n which hath a thouſand times experienced what it is to yeelde to temptation, ought once at the leaſt to try what it is to ouercome temptation.</p>
            <p>Beleeue not becauſe that thou art tempted, that God hath forſaken thee or leſſe regardeth thee, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compteth thee the leſſe righteous and perfect. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that Paul after he ſaw the diuine eſſence, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the temptation of the fleſh, wherwith God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him to be tempted, leſt he ſhould be tempted of pride. Wherein man ought to conſider, that Paul which was an elect veſſell, and taken vp euen to the third heauen, yet he was tried, leſt he ſhould glory in himſelfe, as he teſtifieth of himſelfe, leſt the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of reuelations ſhould exalt me, there was giuen vnto me a pricke in the fleſh to buffet me. Wherefore aboue all temptations, man principally ought to arme himſelfe againſt the temptation of pride, for that it is the roote of all miſchiefe, againſt the which there is one onely remedy, alwaies to remember that God humbled himſelfe for vs, euen vnto the death of the croſſe, and death wil humble vs, though againſt our willes, to be euen meate for wormes.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Twelue weapons of Iohn Picus, Earle of Mirandula, for the ſpirituall battel, which man alwaies ought to haue in a readines, when the deſire of ſinne temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him.</head>
               <item>1 Of ſinne, the pleaſure ſhort and ſmall.</item>
               <item>2 The companions, lothſomnes and anxietie.</item>
               <item>3 Loſſe of a greater good.</item>
               <item>4 Life, a ſleepe and a ſhadowe.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:176514:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>5 Death, at hand, and ſodaine.</item>
               <item>6 The dout of impenitencie.</item>
               <item>7 Eternall reward: eternall paine.</item>
               <item>8 The dignitie and nature of man.</item>
               <item>9 The peace of a good minde.</item>
               <item>10 The benefites of God.</item>
               <item>11 The croſſe of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>12 The teſtimonie of martyres, and the example of holy men.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Twelue conditions of a louer, by Iohn Picus of Mirandula.</head>
               <item>1 To loue one onely, and to deſpiſe all things for him</item>
               <item>2 To thinke him vnhappie which is not with his beloued.</item>
               <item>3 To ſuffer all things, yea death to be with him.</item>
               <item>4 To adorne himſelfe to pleaſe him.</item>
               <item>5 To be with him in all ſortes we may, if not in body, at leaſt wiſe in minde.</item>
               <item>6 To loue all things that pleaſeth him, his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, his councell, his doctrine.</item>
               <item>7 To ſeeke his praiſe, and not to ſuffer any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of him.</item>
               <item>8 To beleeue the beſt of him in all thinges, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all men ſo to beleeue.</item>
               <item>9 To be willing to ſuffer any diſcommoditie for his ſake, taking it in very good part.</item>
               <item>10 To ſhed teares with him often, either for griefe if he be abſent, or for ioy if he be preſent.</item>
               <item>11 To languiſh often, and often to be enflamed with his loue.</item>
               <item>12 To obey him, thinking nothing of reward or recompence.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:176514:10"/>We are accuſtomed to be induced to this chieflie for three cauſes. The firſt is, when the ſeruice is ſuch as of it ſelfe it is to be deſired. The ſecond, when as he whom we obey, is of himſelfe very good and amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that we euen loue and reuerence him for his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. The third is, when he, before we did beginne to ſerue him, hath beſtowed many great benefites vpon vs, and theſe three are in God, becauſe for his ſeruice there is no trauaile taken which is not good for vs, both for our ſoule and body: for that to obey him, is no other thing then to direct our ſelues vnto him that is the chiefeſt God. He is alſo the beſt, comlieſt and wiſeſt, hauing all conditions accuſtomably mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs to loue, and to obey freely: which moſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially hath dealt with vs, in creating vs of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and redeeming vs from hell by the bloud of his ſonne when wee were worſe then nothing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:176514:10"/>
            <head>THE COMMENTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>of Iohn Picus Mirandula, vpon</hi> the ſixteene Pſalme. Pſal. 16.</head>
            <q>Preſerue me O God.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any man being perfect, will call in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt his eſtate, hee muſt take heede of this, that hee boaſt not himſelfe. Dauid therefore, ſpeaking in the perſon of the iuſt man, beginneth of his ſtate in this word: Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me. Which rightly conſidered, taketh away all occaſion of pride: for hee which can attaine to any thing of him ſelfe, can alſo of himſelfe preſerue that thing for himſelfe. Hee therefore which deſireth of God to be kept in the ſtate of vertue, ſignifieth by this that from the beginning he gote not that vertue of himſelfe. And hee which recordeth that he hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned vertue not by his owne power, but by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God, cannot exalt himſelfe of it: but the more humble himſelfe before God, according to that of the Apoſtle, What haſt thou that thou haſt not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? and if thou haſt receiued it, why boaſteſt thou as though thou receiuedſt it not? There are two wordes which wee ought alwaies to haue in our mouth. The one, haue mercie vpon me O God, when that we remember our badnes. The other, preſerue me O God, when we call to minde his goodnes.</p>
            <q>For I haue truſted in thee.</q>
            <p>This is one thing that cauſeth vs to obteyne of God that which we deſire: that is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue a ſure hope to obteyne. And if we obſerue theſe two points,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176514:11"/>
that we neuer deſire of God but thoſe things which are for our good, and that wee earneſtly aske that thing we deſire, not doubting but that God heareth vs, our prayers ſhall neuer be in vaine. Therfore when we obtaine not, it is either for that it is hurtfull for vs, for we know not what to ask, according to Chriſts ſaying: And Ieſus ſaith, Whatſoeuer ye ſhall aske in my name it ſhalbe geuen vnto you for this name Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus doeth ſignifie a Sauiour, and therefore nothing is asked in his name, but it is to the ſauing health of him that asketh, or becauſe wee are not harde, for that in asking good things, we aske not them as wee ought, but wauering in hope, and he whoſe hope is doubtful hath a colde petition: therfore ſaith Iames, Let him aske in faith, doubting nothing.</p>
            <q>I haue ſayd vnto the Lord, thou art my God.</q>
            <p>After he armeth himſelfe againſt pride, he begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to deſcribe his eſtate. The whole ſtate of a good man conſiſteth in this word: I haue ſayd to the Lord, thou art my God. The which word although it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth almoſt common among all men, yet fewe there are which can truely ſay it. Euery man hath that for his God which he counteth for chiefeſt good, which onely had, we thinke our ſelues happy: if all other thinges are wanting, and if that one thing be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, yea if we haue all things els that are good, wee thinke our ſelues vnhappy. The couetous man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith vnto his money, thou art my God: for if he want honor, health, vertue and friendes, ſo hee hath money he is content: and if hee haue all thoſe good things which we haue rehearſed and want money, he thinketh himſelfe a wretch. The glutton alſo ſaith to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176514:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his bellie: the incontinent to his luſt: the ambitious to ſuperioritie and glorie: Thou art my God. See therefore how fewe there be which can ſay, I haue ſaid vnto the Lord, thou art my God. He onely can doe this, whom God onely doeth ſuffice: ſo that if all the kingdomes of the world, and all heauenly and earthly things were ſet before him, yea to offend his God but once, he would not take them. In this word therefore conſiſteth the whole ſtate of a righteous man.</p>
            <q>For thou ſtandeſt not in neede of my goods.</q>
            <p>He yealdeth a reaſon wherefore hee ſaith onely to the Lord, thou art my God. The reaſon is, for that onely God hath no neede of our goods, for there is no creature which wanteth not the help of other cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures, farre more imperfect then it ſelfe, as Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers and Diuines affirme, becauſe if one had not beene, the other had not beene, for confounde part of that which is called vniuerſall, and confounde the whole. The whole being confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, all the parts are confounded. All creatures are part of one vniuerſal, of the which God himſelfe is no part, but the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nothing depending vpon it, for God hath got nothing by the creation of the world, neither ſhould he loſe any thing if the whole world were brought to nought. Therefore God alone hath no neede of our goods. We ought therefore to take ſhame to account him for God which ſtandeth in neede of vs, ſuch is euery creature. Furthermore, we ought not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for God, that is, for the chiefeſt good, but that wherein is the chiefeſt good, but in no creature is the chiefeſt good, therefore wee ought onely to ſay vnto the Lord, Thou art my God.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:176514:12"/>
            <q>But to the ſaints that are in the earth.</q>
            <p>Next vnto God wee ought to loue thoſe moſt which are moſt neare vnto God: ſuch are the angels, and the bleſſed in the celeſtiall Ieruſalem, our lande, kingdome and countrey. Therefore after he ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, thou art my God, he addeth.</p>
            <q>He hath made wonderfull his pleaſure.</q>
            <p>That is, he hath made his loue woonderfull, and his good will toward the Saints which are in his land, that is, in the celeſtiall countrey, which is called the land of God, and the land of the liuing. And if wee truelie conſider what great felicitie his Countrey yealdeth, and what great miſery this world bringeth, and the great goodnes and excellencie of thoſe Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, we ſhall alwayes deſire to part from hence, to be dwelling there. Theſe and ſuch like when we me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate vpon, wee ought alwayes to prouide that our meditations become not vnprofitable. For we ought of euery meditation to reape ſome fruite: as for an example, when we enter into meditation of that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Countrey, we ought to get this benefite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by not onely to be ſtrong to ſuffer death, and patient when by courſe of nature the houre ſhall come, or if it be before to be ſuffered for the faith of Chriſt, but alſo to wiſh it willingly, deſiring to part hence from this vale of miſerie, and ſo to raigne in that bleſſed land with God and his Saints. When therefore, the iuſt man hath deſcribed his ſtate, which is wholy in affection toward God, and things pertayning to his diuine maieſtie, hee alſo from his heart deſpiſeth the ſtate of wicked men, and ſaith:</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:176514:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <q>Their infirmities are multiplied.</q>
            <p>By infirmities he vnderſtandeth Idols, and ſo hath the Hebrew text: for euen as a good man hath one God whom he loueth and reuerenceth: ſo bad and wicked men haue many gods and Idols, and becauſe there are many pleaſures, many deſires, diuers paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which they obey, they therefore ſeeke diuers pleaſures, becauſe no one ſufficeth them. The wicked therefore wander about: and hee addeth, they made haſte after, that is, after their deſires: they headlong and inconſiderately fell: whereby we are taught that we make no leſſe ſpeede to vertue, then they doe to vice: neither with leſſe diligence ſerue and obey our God, then they their Lord the deuill. The iuſt man conſidering the ſtate of wicked men, doeth aſſuredly purpoſe, as we alwayes ought to doe, neuer to folow their waies, and ſaith:</p>
            <q>I wil make no account of their bloudy ſacrifices, neither wil I make mention of them within my lips.</q>
            <p>Hee ſpeaketh of bloud, aſwell for that Idolaters were accuſtomed, hauing gathered the bloud of their ſacrifices, to exerciſe therewith their ceremonies, as alſo for that the whole life of the wicked (the right vſe of reaſon being left) followeth ſenſualitie, which conſiſteth in bloud. He hath ſaid that he will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not doe ſacrifice vnto Idols, but alſo not name them, (which onely without offence can be ſayd and done:) ſhewing by this, that a perfect man ought not onely to abſtaine from vnlawfull pleaſures, but alſo from thoſe which are lawfull: that his minde may the rather be ſetled in heauen, and geuen more purely to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176514:13"/>
the contemplation of heauenly things, and leſt that any ſhould deeme it meere folly to depriue himſelf of all pleaſure, he addeth.</p>
            <q>The Lord is the portion of mine inheritance.</q>
            <p>As if he had ſaid, maruell not if I forgoe all other things to enioy God, in whom all other good things are enioyed. Theſe ought to be the words of euerie Chriſtian: The Lord is the portion of mine inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Becauſe we Chriſtians to whom God is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for an inheritance, ought to be aſhamed to deſire any thing beſide him: and leaſt that it ſhould ſeeme preſumption to any to aſſure this vnto himſelfe, he addeth the ſame.</p>
            <q>Thou art he which doeſt geue me mine inheritance.</q>
            <p>As if he had ſaid, O Lord my God, I know well that I am nothing in reſpect of thee, by mine owne endeuours I am not able to aſcend to enioy thee, but thou art he which doeſt draw me vnto thee through thy grace, and thou art he which geueſt thy ſelfe to me to be inherited. Let the iuſt man then conſider how great is this felicitie, that God ſhalbe his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. He addeth.</p>
            <q>The lots haue fallen to me in goodly places.</q>
            <p>For euery mans part and portion of olde time, was deuided by lottes: And becauſe there are many which although they are called to this felicitie, as are all Chriſtians, yet notwithſtanding they make no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of it, ſo that oftentimes for a little light plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176514:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they change it. He addeth the ſame.</p>
            <q>My heritage is excellent vnto me.</q>
            <p>As if he had ſaid, euen as that heritage is excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo doe I eſteeme it exceeding well, and doe repute all other things in reſpect of it, according to the ſaying of Paule, but very dong: but becauſe to haue this light of vnderſtanding, that man may know this feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie is a gift geuen from God, he therefore addeth.</p>
            <q>I will thanke the Lord for geuing me to vnderſtand.</q>
            <p>For becauſe man oftentimes purpoſeth to ſerue God according to humane reaſon, when ſenſualitie and the fleſh repugne. But that man is perfect that hath not only his ſoule, but alſo his fleſh enclined vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, according to that ſaying: My heart and my fleſh haue reioyced in the liuing God. Therefore hee addeth.</p>
            <q>My reynes alſo chaſten me in the night ſeaſon.</q>
            <p>That is, the very reynes themſelues, wherein is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed the greateſt inclination to concupiſcence, doe not moue me to euil, but rather rebuke and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten me: that is, they withhold me in the night ſeaſon, inſomuch that they tame and ſcourge the very body. Then he ſheweth the cauſe, and ſaith.</p>
            <q>J ſet the Lord alwaies in my ſight.</q>
            <p>For if any man haue God alwaies before his eies,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176514:14"/>
for a rule of all his works: and in all his works he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not his owne commoditie, nor glory, nor plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but onely to pleaſe God: he ſhall in ſhort time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a perfect man: and becauſe he ſo doeth in al his affaires, he ſhall alwaies proſper. Therfore he ſaith.</p>
            <q>He is on my right hand that I can not be moued.</q>
            <p>Hee ſheweth how that the felicitie of a iuſt man is great, becauſe he ſhalbe for euer happie both in ſoule and body: and therefore he addeth.</p>
            <q>My heart is mery.</q>
            <p>That is to ſay, my ſoule is merrie: knowing after death heauen to be prepared for him.</p>
            <q>And my fleſh ſhall reſt in hope.</q>
            <p>That is, although it reioyceth not, as if it were out of hand after death to receiue his ſtate, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it reſteth in the graue with this hope, that it ſhall riſe in the day of iudgement, together with his ſoule, immortall and moſt glorious, and this he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth in the verſe following, for becauſe he ſaid his heart was merry, he geueth a reaſon.</p>
            <q>Becauſe he ſhall not leaue my ſoule in hell.</q>
            <p>And becauſe that hee ſaid his fleſh reſted in hope, he yealdeth a reaſon, ſaying.</p>
            <q>Neither wilt thou ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption.</q>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:176514:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Becauſe that which was corruptible ſhall riſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, and bicauſe Chriſt was the firſt which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Paradiſe, and made the way for vs, and was the firſt which roſe, and his reſurrection is the cauſe of our reſurrection: therefore theſe things which wee haue ſpoken of are principallie to be vnderſtoode of the reſurrection of Chriſt, as Peter the Apoſtle decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. And ſecondly, they are to be vnderſtoode of vs, in as much as we are members of Chriſt which onely ſaw no corruption, becauſe his body was not putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the graue. Therefore, becauſe the way of well liuing leadeth vs into perpetuall life both of ſoule and bodie. He therefore addeth.</p>
            <q>Thou haſt made the wayes of life knowen vnto me.</q>
            <p>And becauſe the whole felicitie of this life conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the true viſion and fruition of God, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore addeth.</p>
            <q>Thou ſhalt fill me with the ioy of thy countenance.</q>
            <p>And becauſe the felicitie ſhall endure for euer, he therefore addeth.</p>
            <q>At thy right hand are pleaſures for euermore.</q>
            <p>He ſaith, at thy right hand, becauſe our felicitie is compleated in the ſight and enioying of Chriſtes hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, which ſitteth at the right hand of the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of God on high, according to that of Iohn. This is our ful reward, to ſee God, and him whom he hath ſent, Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:176514:15"/>
            <head>TO HIS NEPHEW, Iohn Franciſcus, Iohn Picus Earl <hi>of Mirandula, wiſheth health in him</hi> which is the true health.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aruaile not my Sonne, neither take any griefe, or diſmaye, that vpon thy departure from me, there are ſo many occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of euill miniſtred vnto thee, which may diſquiet thee, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande thy determined purpoſe of good life: how greate a myracle ſhould it be rather, if to thee alone amongſt mortall men, the way to heauen were made plaine and eaſie, without labour and toyle, as though there were no deceitful world nor wicked deuill, or as though thou were not yet in the fleſh, which luſteth againſt the ſpirite, and maketh vs of men monſters: vnleſſe wee ſhall looke well to our ſelues: but rather reioyce, as S. Iames counſelleth thee, ſaying, <hi>Reioyce my brethren when yee ſhall fall into diuers temptations.</hi> Nor without good cauſe, for what hope is there of glory, when there wanteth hope of victorie: and what victory can
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176514:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
there be when there is no fight. Hee is lured to the crowne, that is allured to the combat, and eſpecially to ſuch wherein no man can be ouercome, if hee will not himſelfe: neither neede we any mans help to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere, but onely his, which geueth vs both mind and might to ouercome. It is great felicitie to a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, to conſider that the victorie conſiſteth by the goodnes of God in his owne will, and the rewardes thereof farre greater then either his wiſh or worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe poſsiblie may be. Tell me (my deare Sonne) is there any thing in this life, of theſe things, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire troubleth earthly mindes, that can bee attayned without labor, or not enduring many indignities and miſeries. The merchant thinketh it well with him, if after many nauigations, many thouſand diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, thouſand perils of life, he get ſome gayne. It needeth not that I write vnto thee as touching the warfare of this world, whoſe miſeries experience it ſelfe hath and doeth ſufficiently teach thee. What heapes of griefes, what great anxietie, how much carefulnes there is in obteyning the fauour of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in purchaſing the friendſhip of our equals, in compaſsing of honors, I am rather for to learne of thee, then to teach thee: who contenting my ſelfe and meane leiſure with my bookes, haue learned from my very youth to liue within my bounds. Theſe therefore earthly, tranſitorie, vncertaine and vile things, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon alſo to vs with brute beaſts, ſhall we with paine and panting ſcarcely attaine: and ſhall we be drawen as if we were drouſie and ſleepy, and as it were againſt our will vnto heauenly and diuine things, the which eye hath not ſeene, nor the eare heard, as if without vs the Lord could not raigne, neither thoſe heauenlie Citizens be euer bleſſed. Truely, if this earthly felicity might be got with eaſe, a man might (ſhunning la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour)
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176514:16"/>
like better to ſerue the world then God. But if we are nothing the leſſe, yea much more then in the way of God wearied in the way of ſinners (whereof is that ſaying of the damned, we are tyred in the way of iniquitie) it cannot be but extreame madnes to bee more vnwilling to labour where reward is rendered, then where for our labor puniſhment is ordeyned. I omitte to ſhew how great the peace and felicitie of the mind is to know it ſelfe cleere in conſcience, free from fault: the which doubtleſſe is farre more to bee eſteemed then all the pleaſures that may be enioyed or wiſhed in this life: what is worthy the wiſhing for in theſe worldly pleſures, which, while they are a ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, they defatigate: and being obteyned, doe infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuat: &amp; being loſt, doe excruciat. Doubteſt thou, my ſonne, that the mindes of the wicked are not toſſed with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual care, it is the word of God, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deceiued nor deceiue: the hart of the wicked is as it were the raging ſea that taketh no reſt, for there is nothing vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſafe, nothing peaceable: all things import vnto them feare, care, death: ſhall we therfore enuie theſe? ſhall we haue theſe in emulation, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting our proper dignitie, our countrey, and our heauenly father, ſhall we, when as we are borne free, become their ſlaues and bondmen, that liuing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them miſerably, dying more miſerably, at length in eternal fire we may be tormented moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably? O the blinde mindes and hearts of men! who is he that ſeeth not trueth it ſelfe, yet neuertheleſſe leaue we vndone the things which we know are to be done. Doubt not my ſonne, but eſpecially in thoſe places wherein thou remayneſt, innumerable impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments will beſet thee, and driue thee if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, from thy purpoſe of liuing a holy and godly life, and fling thee downe headlong if thou takeſt not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:176514:16"/>
very good heede: but among the reſt, it is a deadlie plague day and night to be conuerſant among thoſe, whoſe life is not onely in euery parte an enticement to ſinne, but wholy ſet and placed vnder the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror the deuill, vnder the ſtanderd of death, vnder the ſalarie of hell, in expugnation of vertue, fighteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt heauen, againſt the Lord, &amp; againſt his Chriſt. But crie thou out with the Prophet, <hi>Let vs breake their bonds aſunder, and caſt away their cords from vs.</hi> For theſe are they whom the Lord hath deliuered vp into their hearts luſt, and into a reprobate ſence, to doe thoſe things which are not conuenient, being full of all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes, fornication, wickednes, couetouſnes, maliciouſnes, full of enuie, of murder, of debate, of deceite, taking all things in the euill part, whiſperers, backbiters, haters of God, dooers of wrong, proude boaſters, inuenters of euil things, without vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ill natured, without naturall affection, without faithfulnes, without mercie. Which men when they dayly ſaw the righteouſnes of God, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, they vnderſtoode not how that they which doe thoſe things are worthy of death, not only thoſe that doe them, but alſo they which doe fauor ſuch as doe them. Pleaſe not thou therefore, my ſonne, whom vertue diſpleaſeth, but let that ſaying of the Apoſtle be alwaies before thine eyes, <hi>It behooueth vs to pleaſe God rather then man.</hi> And alſo that of the Apoſtle: <hi>If I ſhould ſtudie to pleaſe men, I ſhould not then be the ſeruaunt of God.</hi> Let a certaine kinde of godly ambition inuade thee, and vouchſafe not them worthie to be maſters of thy life, who were fitter to be thy ſchollers: For it is farre decenter that they begin to be men by liuing well with thee, then that thou omitting thy good purpoſe, ſhouldeſt become a beaſt by liuing ill with them. There holdeth me (I take God to witnes) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176514:17"/>
as it were an extaſie, and a certaine kinde of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment, when I begin, I know not whether ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to thinke vpon, or to be ſory for, to admire or to deplore the ſtudies of men: (or to ſpeake more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) their meere madnes. For truely it is meere madnes not to beleeue the Goſpell: the trueth whereof the bloud of Martyrs crieth, the voice of the Apoſtles ſoundeth, miracles proueth, reaſon confirmeth, the world witneſſeth, the elements ſhew, the deuils con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe. But it is farre greater madnes if thou doeſt not doubt of the trueth of the Goſpell, to liue notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as though thou doubtedſt nothing of the falſenes thereof. For if thoſe words be true, that it is moſt harde for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of heauen, why doe we then daily buſie our ſelues in heaping vp riches: and if it bee true, that the glorie which is not of man but of God is to be ſought, why doe we then alwayes hang &amp; depend vpon the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men. There is no man that careth to pleaſe God, &amp; if we ſtedfaſtly beleue that the time wil come when the Lord ſhall ſay, <hi>Goe ye curſed into euerlaſting fire,</hi> and againe, <hi>Come ye bleſſed, and poſſeſſe the Kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world.</hi> Why doe we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either feare nothing leſſe then hel, or hope for nothing leſſe then heauen: what els can be ſaid, but that there be many Chriſtians in name, but very fewe in deede. Striue thou, my ſonne, to enter in by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row gate, and geue not heede to that which many men doe, but to that which ought for to be done, the which the law of nature, reaſon, and God him ſelfe will ſhew thee. For thy glorie ſhall not be the leſſe, if thou be happie, with a fewe, nor thy puniſhment the lighter if thou bee miſerable with many. There are two moſt principal preſent remedies for thee againſt the world and the deuill, with the which, as with two
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176514:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
wings thou ſhalt flye vp on high from the valley of teares, that is to ſay, almes and prayer: for what can we doe without the helpe of God: or how ſhall hee helpe being not called vpon. And moreouer, he will not heare thee calling vpon him, which haſt not firſt heard the poore calling vpon thee. For it is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet that God deſpiſe thee, being a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who being a man, haſt deſpiſed a man. It is written, <hi>With what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ye meate, ſhall other men meaſure to you againe.</hi> And elſwhere, <hi>Bleſſed are the merciful, for they ſhal obteine mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</hi> But when I inuite thee to prayer, I doe not inuite thee to that which conſiſteth in much babbling: but to that which ſpeaketh to God within the ſecrete cloſet of the minde, in the priuie chamber of the hart, with affection moſt earneſt, and in the moſt bright clowde of contemplation, doeth not onely preſent the minde vnto God, but it doeth by certaine ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meanes vnite it faſt, which the experienced onely know. Neither doe I waigh how long thy prayer be, but how effectuall and how earneſt it be, interlaced rather with ſighes, then poured out with a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all order and number of words. If thou regardeſt thy ſaluation or wilt be free from the ſnares of the deuil, from the ſtormes of the world, from the ambuſhes of thy enemies, if thou deſireſt to be accepted of God, and ſo at length to become happie, ſee that no daye paſſe wherein once, at the leaſt, thou makeſt not thy prayers vnto God, and proſtrating thy ſelfe with the humble affection of a godly minde, crieſt not out with the Prophet, not outwardly from thy lips, but inwardly from thy heart: <hi>Remember not the offences and ignorances of my youth, but according to thy mercie, for thy goodnes ſake, remember me O Lord.</hi> The ſpirite ſhall teach thee, which maketh requeſt for vs, and alſo neceſsitie euery houre what thou ſhalt aske of God, ſacred rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176514:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhall alſo helpe, which I pray thee moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe, ſetting aſide the vaine fables and triflinges of Poets. There is nothing more acceptable with God, nothing more profitable for thy ſelfe, as day &amp; night to haue in hand the holy Scripture. In it there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine celeſtiall and heauenly power, liuely &amp; effectual, which doeth transforme the minde of the Reader, ſo that he vſe it purely &amp; humbly, into a diuine &amp; godly loue, by a moſt wonderfull vertue. But I haue now exceeded the limits of an Epiſtle, the matter and the affection drawing me therto, which I haue alwais had toward thee: eſpecially from that houre wherin I was firſt certified of thy moſt godly purpoſe. Laſtly, I will admoniſh thee of that which when thou waſt with me I haue often ſpoken of to thee: that is, that thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forget theſe two thinges: the ſonne of God to haue died for thee, and that thou (though thou liue long) art ſhortly to die. With theſe two, as it were with two ſpurres, the one of feare, the other of loue, driue thy horſe through the ſhort race of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary life, vnto the gole of eternall felicitie, when as we neither ought, nor can prefixe any other ende vnto our ſelues, as then to enioy in both body and ſoule, perpetuall peace without end: by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite goodnes of him which is both God and man, Chriſt Ieſus. Farewell. Feare God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:176514:18"/>
            <head>John Picus Earle of Mirandula, wiſheth health to Iohn Franciſcus his Nephew.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou art happy, my ſonne, when as GOD hath not onely geuen thee grace to lyue well, but by liuing well in the meane time to heare ill at wicked mens hands, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe thou liueſt well. It is an equall praiſe by the commendable to be commended, and to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the condemnable. But I therefore account thee not happie in that this reproache is glorious vnto thee, but becauſe our Lord Ieſus Chriſt is true: yea trueth it ſelfe affirmeth, that our reward ſhalbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant in heauen, when men ſhall ſpeake euill of vs, and ſhall falſly ſay all maner of euill ſaying againſt vs for his names ſake. This is an Apoſtolicall dignity, to be accounted worthie to ſuffer reproch for the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels ſake. We reade in Luke, that the Ahoſtles went out reioyſing from the ſight of the counſell, becauſe they were thought worthie to ſuſtain and endure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch and contumelie for the name of Ieſus. Let vs therefore reioice if that wee are accounted worthie with God, ſo great glorie as to haue his glorie mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by our ignominie, and if we ſuſtaine any thing hard or troubleſome of the world, let that moſt ſweete voice of the Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort vs, <hi>If the world hate you, knowe ye that it hated me before you.</hi> If the world hated him by whom it was made, ſhall we moſt vile men (and if we conſider our wickednes, moſt worthie all reproches) if any detract or ſpeake euill, take it greeuouſly, and to ſtop the wicked tongue, ſhall wee beginne to liue wickedly? Let vs therefore rather content our ſelues ioyfully with their bad reports, and if our felicity be not ſuch: for vertue ſake, &amp; for true h to ſuffer ſtripes, bonds, priſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſword, as our nobles and worthies
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:176514:19"/>
haue done before vs. Yet let vs thinke it goeth well with vs, if we ſuffer reproches, backbitings and hatred of wicked men, leſt that all occaſion of good ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors being taken from vs, there be no hope of bliſſe left for vs. Furthermore, if men praiſe thee for thy wel liuing, this thy vertue, as it is a vertue, makes thee like vnto Chriſt: but in as much as it is praiſed, it makes thee vnlike, who for a rewarde of his vertue, receiued of men the death of the croſſe, therfore God (ſaith the Apoſtle) exalted him, and gaue him a name which is aboue all names. Therefore it is rather to be wiſhed, to be crucified of the worlde and exalted of God, then to be exalted of the world and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God. The world crucifieth vnto life, God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth to glory. The world exalteth to ruine, the Lord iudgeth to hell. To conclude, if the world flatter and fawne vpon thee, it can ſcarce be that vertue, which altogether erected vpward, ought to haue God onely for to pleaſe, doe not encline it ſelfe ſomewhat to the plauſible fauor of men: and if it looſe nothing of his integritie, yet it looſeth ſomewhat of his reward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when it beginneth to bee performed in earth, where all things are little, the leſſe ſhalbe rendered in heauen, where all things are great. Happie are the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches that cauſe ſafetie, that neither the floure of righteouſneſſe wither with the peſtiferous winde of vaine glorie, nor the ſtipende of eternitie be dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the vaine applauſure of popular fame. Let vs, my ſonne, embrace theſe contumelies, and as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the Lord with a moſt holy kinde of ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let vs triumph, but in the ignominie of the croſſe of Chriſt. We preach (ſaith S. Paul) Chriſt crucified, to the Hebrewes an offence, to the Gentiles fooliſhnes, but to vs the vertue &amp; wiſdome of God. The wiſdom of this world is fooliſhnes with God, and the fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:176514:19"/>
of Chriſt is that which ouercommeth the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the world, by the which it hath pleaſed God to ſaue as many as beleue. If thou doubteſt not them to be mad which detract thy vertue, and cal Chriſtian life, (that is heauenly wiſdome) madnes, remember then how great thy madnes would be, to be ſeduced from thy determined courſe in liuing well, by the iudgement of mad men, whereas euery error is to be taken away by correction, not enlarged by imitation. Let them neigh, let them baule, let them barke, goe thou on luſtely thy iourney, and weigh by their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes how much thou art indebted vnto God, who hath enlightened thee that ſateſt in the ſhadowe of death, and tranſlated from their companie, who wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and wallowed here and there out of the waye without a guide in moſt obſcure darkenes, hath aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated thee with the ſonnes of light. Let that moſt ſweete voyce of the Lord alwaies ſound in thy eares: <hi>Let the dead burie their dead, follow thou me.</hi> They are dead which liue not to God, and in the time of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall death moſt painefully and labouriouſly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe to themſelues eternall death: of whom if thou demaundeſt whether they goe, how they apply their endeuors, works and cares, and to conclude, what end they haue prefixed and preſcribed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, by the attaining wherof they are become happy, they haue either nothing at al to anſwere, or els they ſpeak words of repugnance and contrarietie to themſelues as it were the dotings of phanatical perſons, neither know they what to doe, but according to the maner of them that ſwim in flouds (by the force of an euill induced cuſtome) they are carried as it were with the rage of a ſtreame: on the one ſide iniquitie blinding them, on the other ſide Sathan prouoking them to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, fall downe headlong into all miſchiefe, being
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176514:20"/>
blinde guides of the blinde, vntill death vnawares take them, and it be ſaid vnto them, Frend, this night will they require thy ſoule of thee, but whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt prouided? Then they commend thoſe whom they condemned, then they praiſe thoſe whom they deſpiſed, and would imitate thoſe when they cannot, whom when they might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, they had rather purſue. Liſten not, my deare ſonne, to what men ſhall either ſay or thinke of thee, account it nothing, only view in thy mind the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, which he will geue to euery man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his workes, in his reuelation from heauen, with Angels and powers, taking vengeance on al with fiery flames which haue not knowen God, &amp; obeyed his Goſpell, which (as the Apoſtle ſaith) ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for euer from the face of God, and from the glorie of his vertue, when hee ſhall come to be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in his ſaints, and to be made wonderfull in all them which haue beleeued. It is written, <hi>Feare not him which is able to deſtroy the body, but him which is able to caſt thy ſoule downe to hell.</hi> But how much leſſe art thou to feare them which are able neither to hurte the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy nor ſoule, who if they now backbite thee gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by reaſon, they will not the leſſe backbite thee, if thou ſhouldeſt leaue to be vertuous, and come to be vicious, not becauſe vice diſpleaſeth them, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the vice of backbiting alwayes pleaſeth them. Shunne, if thou haſt any care of thy ſoules health, ſhun as much as thou canſt their companie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to thy ſelfe, often pray thou in ſecrete vnto thy moſt mercifull father, crying out with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Vnto thee O Lord haue I lift vp my ſoule, my God in thee doe I truſt, I will not be aſhamed though mine enemies mocke me and ſcorne me, for all that hope and trust in thee shall not be confounded. Let them be confounded that doe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176514:20"/>
wickedly: teach me thy waies, O Lord, and shew me thy paths, direct me in thy trueth, and teach mee, for thou art God my Sauiour, in thee will I alwaies truſt.</hi> See alſo that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member death to be at hand, and the ſmall time wee haue to liue, yea leſſe then a geometricall poynt: then how euill that auncient enemie is, which promiſeth vs the kingdomes of the world, that hee might take from vs the kingdome of heauen: how falſe pleaſures are which imbrace vs to the end to ſtrangle vs: how deceitfull are honors, which lift vs vp to caſt vs down: how deadly are riches, which the more they feede vs, the more they poyſon vs: how ſhort, how vncertaine, how wauering, how falſe, how fantaſtike is all that which all theſe together had at wiſh, are able to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh vnto vs. How great things are promiſed &amp; prouided for theſe, which deſpiſing the preſents, ſeek that Countrey, whoſe king is Deitie, whoſe law is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, whoſe maner is eternitie. With theſe and ſuch like cogitations occupie thy minde, which will ſtirre thee vp ſleeping, kindle thee cooling, confirme thee ſtaggering, and yeeldeth vnto thee winges of godly loue, tending to heauen, that when thou ſhalt come vnto vs, the which we al expect with earneſt deſire we may not only ſee thee whom we would, but alſo ſuch as we would. Farewell, and loue God, whom thou haſt ſo begun.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
